[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right welcome to the stoa
i'm peter lindberg the steward of the
stoa and it still has a place for us to
coherent dialogue about what
matters most at the nice edge of this
very moment
and today we have a very special guest
derek jensen uh derek at least according
to his
wikipedia bio is a radical
environmentalist and an
anti-civilization advocate
uh democracy now labeled him a poet
philosopher of the ecology movement
um he's the author of many books uh and
i have all of them
a language over the world a culture of
make-believe
what else do we got here end game and
then
what we leave behind uh and
how derek came on my radar i think i was
like
17 i just got out of high school i was
going to university
and i read the language all in world's
uh words and it
blew my mind just opened up to a
different world and it kind of opened me
up to an intellectually rich
life uh and and kind of showed the
seriousness
of the situation we're in so um
and i mean him corresponding on email
back and this is back in 2003 as well
and he gave me some advice on
on writing and stuff so i i appreciate
that um
so how today is going to work is uh
derek and i are going to chat for about
10 20 minutes if you have any questions
throughout throw them in the chats i
will call you to mute yourself
if you don't want to be on youtube
because this will eventually go on
youtube
just indicate that in the chats um be
respectful
uh one follow-up question uh only and if
you know people are kind of muting
themselves and it turns into a [ __ ] show
then i'll take away the unmuting
access from everyone um that being said
i will allow derek to unmute himself
welcome to the stoic derek
thank you for having me and thank you
everybody for showing up
and and derek's on like an old computer
right now so it's like uh
it's a lot of noise you're coming from
it so opportunity for us to
practice our stoicism as always um
so a title of this talk uh is a quote i
got
from someone speaking about your career
i believe
and they said this at some point in his
career everyone
everyone who loves derek jensen's work
is gonna hate him because he refuses to
follow any ideological lines
and takes his thoughts wherever they go
um
so i guess the launching question is why
do you think this individual said this
about you and
what it is what is it about like how you
operate
intellectually that makes this the case
thank you for asking that and one of my
intellectual heroes is lewis mumford
lewis mumford was a very strong
pro-technology uh
advocate in the 1930s and then along
came world war ii
and that profoundly changed his
perspective
before world war ii he believed the
notion that
who controls the technology makes the
difference in how
it is in whether the technology is
helpful or harmful to society
and he saw world war ii and realized
he'd been wrong
and i think it takes great
intellectual courage to
admit you're wrong and to go to go
um to go wherever the facts lead you
and um i'm not saying that i have the
intellectual courage of
louis mumford i just know that
um
that there have been times in my books
where i have written something
and a great example is uh in dreams i
think it was i was really taking richard
dawkins to task and saying some frankly
pretty bad things about richard dawkins
and then i said some worse things about
richard dawkins
and um
i hope they hang up quickly anyway i
said some worse things about richard
dawkins but then i came across
new information about him that made it
so that was
uh what i was saying was wrong so it's
like i gotta pull that
and if you're gonna write a book you
should tell the truth
and if you're going to
um
good if you're going to
[Music]
i i don't understand and it makes me
very frustrated
when
people uh
deny
truths whatever they are do not deny new
evidence to
to fit a preconceived perspective
um i'm thinking of the fact i was raised
a fundamentalist christian
and you know there were very there was
dogma that was sometimes more important
than
than than reality and
i sort of made my bones in the late 80s
early 90s as an environmentalist
and uh during the late 80s and early 90s
one of the big things in the pacific
northwest was uh
the owls versus jobs debate and
i was pretty stunned by the
dishonesty of it because all through the
80s the cut went up and the number of
jobs went down
and it wasn't protecting spotted owls
that was
costing the jobs it was raw log exports
and automation
but people wouldn't talk about that and
i guess i want to back up just a little
bit and i guess one of the reasons i'm
rambling apart from the fact that's what
i do is that um
nobody's ever asked me this particular
question so far and
the
maybe one of the reasons i do this is i
remember when i was in college
um i first gained some disdain
for mainstream medias because me
mainstream
media people mainstream news people
because it seemed like
almost every time they wrote about
something that i knew
apart from sports if they wrote about
something political i knew something
about
um they had their facts wrong
and i have
sort of a terror of
writing something and then it ending up
that
sort of like i think it was emily latel
in the 1970s on saturday night live you
know
never mind because i was
i got my facts wrong so i have a real
terror of that so i try to
[Music]
make the arguments as sound as i can and
then go from there
i don't know if that makes any sense
it does i mean some of it's not really a
political act some of it is just i try
to be careful
and um
and i have great disdain for
those who uh
who will intentionally like spin
things in order to serve their agenda as
opposed to
getting the facts first and then
figuring out where they go and and i
have disdain for myself when i do that
too
you know i just finished yesterday i
finished writing a draft of a book
about how marijuana legalization has
been
and is sort of a great transfer of
wealth from family farmers to big
speculators and
it was tempting in this as i'm saying
you know how how great the family
farmers
of marijuana were it was really tempting
to
ignore the fact that a lot of
underground farmers use
illegal pesticides do some really nasty
stuff
steal from each other so it was really
tempting
not really tempting was slightly
tempting to ignore those to better make
my case
but you know what gotta show our awards
too
and here's one more thing and then i'll
shut up but
i think part of it comes to from i would
rather
find my own flaws in my own arguments
and i would rather point those out
beforehand rather than
have somebody else point it out to me
later
that's a preemptive strike yeah yeah
uh so i see a lot of uh stoic
regulars here and i don't know what
their familiarity is with your work
so i wonder if there's like a 101
on derek jensen his world view that you
can provide us
and then we can kind of dig deeper from
there
um yeah first one is i if i had to sum
up all my books into
i think one sentence it would be uh
this way of living will not last and
when it's over i would rather that there
is more of the world left
left rather than less so that's pretty
much it
um another one is physical reality is
always more important than what we think
about it
and what we think about it can certainly
influence how we behave
in in it but physical reality is always
primary
so we can call warehouse or the tree
growing company but that doesn't make
them the tree growing company
and um
we can call
wind and solar green but that doesn't
make them green
and and in fact that's another thing is
you know i was really heavily influenced
by
um one of the most important interviews
i ever did was with
robert j lifton and he wrote the nazi
doctors
and many other books one of the world's
foremost if not the world's foremost
authority in the psychology of genocide
and one of the things he talks about
extensively
that really influenced me a lot was
the idea that before you can commit any
mass atrocity
you have to convince both yourself and
others that what you're doing is not an
atrocity but instead
good virtuous so according to
the nazis the nazis were not in fact
committing mass murder and genocide but
they were purifying the aryan race
they weren't waging aggressive war they
were
uh gaining laban's realm and
this is true on a personal level too
but i don't know if i'm the only person
here who has never once in my life
been a juror i mean every time that i
have objectively been a jerk i've had
myself fully
convinced that i was acting righteously
and
the other person deserved whatever i did
to them
in other words we can rationalize almost
any behavior which is one of the reasons
i'm way more interested in reality yeah
no no
i'm interested in the rationalizations
but
i recognize that rationalizations
including my own
are just rationalizations and we always
have to come back
to ground we always have to come back to
what is
so in sum this way of living can't last
won't last
and after it's done i'd rather that more
of the world be left rather than less
uh another part is uh
um i don't believe that humans are
particularly special
i mean i i believe the humans are
special but i think the bears are
equally special i think
redwood trees are equally special i i
don't think we are
better than anybody else more deserving
than anybody else
i don't think we're particularly more
intelligent than anybody else i think
that there are
an infinite number of no it's not an
infinite number there's there's a
huge range of vastly different
intelligences
that we cannot uh
that we literally can't conceptualize
and we can't conceptualize what it's
like to be a dog
uh with a sense of smell that is
more important than a sense of vision
and anyway so non-humans
are more important than we give them
credit for
and also uh
larger communities are more important
than individuals such that
um i love paul stamet's line about
nature loves a community
that
i'm not sure that nature loves every
individual because
lots of little tadpoles get eaten before
they turn into frogs
and as an individual
things can get pretty tough but
but the the communities are more
important than
than individuals um
which can have some interesting toxic
mimics in society where we come to
believe that
coca-cola is the corporation is more
important than
individuals that's not what i'm talking
about anyway i'm rambling again
so if there's anything people want to
chew off on any of that that'd be great
um so start throwing your questions in
the chat i'll
call you in a moment um i saw in a video
that's you know summarized
my work video you also said another one
uh uh perpetrators of abuse are
insatiable
oh yeah that's yeah that's i had a
really
you know i like chris hedges and we've
had
some interesting conversations over the
years and
one of the things i find really
interesting is that we have both been
through traumatic experiences human war
and me and
in i was going to say the war against
women and children but you know say
whatever you want in domestic violence
and and we took
complementary
and in some ways very different
uh lessons from it but one of his
lessons
is which i think is a desperately
important lesson
is that um
he he has seen
the basically acts of violence
traumatizing can sometimes destroy
people
and that he has seen
too much uh
too many people destroyed by it he's
lost too many friends
and he doesn't like it
and makes perfect sense to me i
i don't disagree with that at all at the
same time
the perspective i bring which he doesn't
disagree with
is i learned early on the perpetrators
of abuse and this includes
perpetrators of abuse against the planet
are insatiable
they they can never get enough which is
one reason capitalism always has to
expand
um there is no limit and part of that
comes from another writer who really
influenced me very deeply was uh
rd lang uh unfortunately he was
personally
a terrible person but his writing
is very interesting because he describes
abuse perhaps better than anybody else
i've ever known
he himself was a perpetrator anyway
um one of the things he said that i just
loved is
how do you plug avoid plugging a void
and what
i believe he meant by that was if you're
using
let's say you have this profound
loneliness
say and this
loneliness instead of
dealing with it directly you instead
try to fill it with sugar or try to fill
it with
sex or try to fill it with uh
buying things you're using another void
to plug a void
and so
um so you have to keep
performing those same actions over and
over
because you're not getting you're not
uh you're not filling the hole that it's
purporting to fill
which is why consumerism can never
ultimately
substitute for community say
okay um so we've got some questions
populating
keep throwing your questions in chat um
start with margaret
margaret you got a question for derek if
you're going to meet yourself
hi yeah thank you um you mentioned
coming back to what is
and i was curious what your personal
process for that looks like
well i thank you for that question i can
i can go a couple directions with that
one of them is um
is you know my my father was extremely
violent
um he broke my sister's arm my brother
has epilepsy from blows to the head he
raped my mother my sister and me
and i started therapy when i was
28 or 29 and i remember the first thing
the therapist said
is i sat down and
he said so how do you feel right now
and i said what
i don't know what you're talking about
and he said
well uh i'm sitting here and there's a
window behind me and i feel the sun on
my shoulders and that feels good
and you're a new client so i'm a little
bit nervous
and he just talked me through what he
said it's like
oh i can do that
and so
part part of it was
you know simply uh
you know one of the things that that
i did too much when i was an athlete
and i was proud of this as an athlete
but not so good in terms of being in
your body
that you know i broke my foot playing
football and i finished the game and i
broke my hand playing softball and
finished the game
because i would just wall off the pain
and there are times
when that could be life-saving but
a football game or a softball game i
don't think is one of them and
and so i was terribly out of my body and
um and that was a
so so in
in the long scale what got me back into
my body was
12 years of therapy and lots of times of
like of being in a not good relationship
and going into the therapist and saying
so
she did this and this and she called me
this and this and she said i was this
and this
and that doesn't feel very good uh
so am i wrong
or was that inappropriate behavior and
so
i hadn't learned how to do that so so
the therapist helped me to he would say
yeah it's great you know it took you
only four days to realize this was
abusive behavior
and last time it took you three weeks so
that's great and sometime you might be
able to get there in a day
and then sometimes you might be able to
say in the moment hey that's not okay
so there was that
and then now
i mean having gone through that longer
process
of
i mean this is such a buzzword these
days i don't really want to use it of
decolonization i've gone through that
process of
of um sort of vomiting up the effects
of a coercive upbringing i
um now
what i do to get back to it is like when
i'm writing
i will write some rhetorical thing
that's all
fancy and and beautiful sounding or
as beautiful sounding as i can make it
and then
i'll look at it and i'll go but what's
the real truth
it's like there's a friend of mine that
i've edited his
his work for 20
30 years now almost and
um it's a joke between us that
he'll read me something that he's
working on and then
i'll say huh so what are you trying to
say here
and then just forget the rhetoric just
what's real
and then he'll say well i think they're
overcutting the forests of
washington it's like okay we'll just say
that and i do the same thing all the
time but i'll be
i'll be working myself in circles trying
to figure something out
and then i'll say i'll just stop and say
okay
what is true what do i know
and then i'll start and then i'll just
say say that
and then i'll build up from there so for
me now
it's a process of
of
trying to
trying to ask myself pretending that
pretending
pretending that i
am two years old and being a very
annoying or three years old and being a
very annoying child
asking why so if i'm if i say something
it's like
no prove it show that
and then why why is that the case and
then
go to the next level and then say but
why is that the case
and go to the next level and say but why
is that the case and
to sort of work my way back
to what i know is real
kind of like i mean i end up in a
completely different place
but kind of like uh you know descartes
was looking for one thing he could trust
and finally came to
i am here i i am thinking
therefore i exist and
so it's the same except once again i end
up in a completely different place
but i try to look for things that are
solid
and then build up oh here's another way
to say this that
i've always had a terrible rope memory
which is why i did not do so well in
organic
organic chemistry or geology or
mineralogy
because a lot of that is memorizing
nomenclature and stuff
um and so i've been always when i got my
degree in science and physics i was
terrible at memorizing uh
formula and what i had to do
in every test which worked out pretty
well for me
is it was much easier for me to go back
to first principles every time
and uh
and re-derive the formula than it was
for me to memorize the formula
and i'm not saying this i'm not proud of
the fact that oh was great i went back
to first principles every time
it's simply because i didn't have a good
enough memory to to memorize the formula
so so i do that in my life as much as i
can let's go back to first principles
and then build up from there if that
makes any sense
so it's both emotionally
i had to learn how to get into my body
and
intellectually having a poor memory in
some ways
and compensating compensating for that
caused me to uh have to derive things
from first principles
cool um so we had uh two questions
i'll read one and then i'll take and
someone to uh say theirs so
grace wanted me to read this on her
behalf um how do you have conversations
with people unaware that they're caught
in the dominant
culture power over matrix and this might
be similar to
uh jj's questions as well so jj would
you like to unmute yourself and ask your
question
hello terry
um yeah i've been listening to you my
vision too i think you said something
nice but you also crapped out can you
say it again
sure um i just said hello and can he
him me now am i good yeah
maybe turn off your video okay i'll turn
off my video
see all right um so
yeah i've been listening to your work
for years um
as audio as i travel around london and
throughout i've just wanted to kind of
reach out and give you a big hug so
that's the first thing i wanted to say
and yeah because
a lot of what you said i kind of
resonated with um
a lot of kind of how
kind of power kind of reproduces itself
and it reproduces
in the actions we interpersonal actions
we have within our families and stuff
like that
um and so along those lines i'm curious
on what ways you found to navigate your
interpersonal relationships
and um kind of like how that relates to
a wider community kind of approach
community development
cool thank you for your time and thanks
for picking my question
peter well thank you both for those
excellent questions
and um
i think i'm not particularly proud of
this but
i think it reminds me of a question that
i've gotten
a few times which is um
when you when i used to have family
get-togethers which i don't really
anymore now that my mom's dead
when i used to have family get-togethers
what would we talk about
at thanksgiving and
the answer is usually football because
i can't tell you how many thanksgivings
i ruined by
talking about politics with people who
weren't
who weren't uh who were interested in
having a big meal at
all so
so that's part of it and then another
part is and both of these come from the
fact that i think i'm fundamentally
conflict-avoidant i don't really like
conflict so first off i talk about
football or something
and second um
when i talk to somebody that i think
there might be some sort of opening
i will talk about it
in a way where i think that i can gain
some
access through a particular issue
so for example uh there was
a guy at a local computer shop
that i used to chat with him sometimes
when i would go in to get my computer
fixed
and he and i would not
uh talk about the death of the salmon
because i knew he didn't care
on the other hand we would talk about i
would raise the subject of
how he feels about big box stores
destroying local businesses because
walmart eventually drove him out of
business
so if you so i try to think tactically
and find ways that
we can raise issues
that uh that the person can think about
over time
and here's another thing that really
guides my interactions on those i read
somewhere
that it takes 10 years to change your
mind and
this guy was very strongly anti-choice
on abortion and then about 10 years
later he found himself very strongly
pro-choice without having had any sort
of discernible transition
and i realized that that's in many ways
how i
changed my mind too that like when john
livingston first introduced me to the
idea that
nature is primarily based on cooperation
not primarily based on competition
i thought he was nuts and i didn't say
that to him i just listened to him
and thought wow
he had some good things to say at one
point but now he's going over the edge
and it wasn't ten years for me it was
about three years about three years
later i could no longer conceptualize
that uh that evolution is based
primarily on competition sure there are
elements of competition but but that's
not the primary
driver and my point of bringing all that
up
is that i don't really argue with people
what i will do is i will make points i
will drop things in
and then i just walk away because
very very very very rarely
is someone in the moment convinced by
argument
instead what will happen and this
happens my friends this happens so often
that my friends are all
used to it by now and they just laugh at
me that my friend will tell me something
say have my friend will have this great
idea oh such and such and such
about you know nature or something i'll
go nah that's not how it works
and then about eight months later i'll
go up to that same friend and i'll say
hey
i had this great idea and i basically
say the same thing back to them that
they said to me eight months ago that i
disagreed with
and my friends know this and my friends
so they don't argue with me in the
moment either because they know eight
months later i'm gonna come back and
and then when they remind me you know i
said that to you it's like oh yeah you
did
um and i think that that's really how we
learn
is by having some idea challenged
and then i love the word rumination
like you know it's like cows you know
send the food down
and then they bring it back up and they
chew on it again and then they swallow
it
and then they bring it back up and chew
on it and i think that's how we really
learn
is by somebody says something we go huh
and then we send it down we metabolize
it for a while and then we bring it up
and chew on it
and then we swallow it we metabolize it
for a while
and then eventually we have a brand new
idea that is entirely ours alone
even though somebody said it to us a
year ago
so so i try to i i don't argue i just
i can build a case but then if i find
there is
a strong resistance to it great
wow that was a good game yesterday for
the nuggets and the lakers really close
man i thought the nuggets were going to
win
thanks thanks for that
well thanks for the question all right
uh
who's next dude i think uh
daniel lockhart if you can oh
ask it for him derek it has been many
years since i've engaged in your work
i know a lot of what you do is under
radar by necessity
but if you could please speak about
wedges any wedges or levers
or well-placed monkey wrenches
coronavirus responses have revealed or
highlighted
well my work has to be all above ground
and
so i'm actually very public
about things um oh gosh maybe 15 years
ago
i got a call from a defense attorney for
one of the green scare people
saying i got an email from him saying we
need to talk
i'm like crap that is that is the email
you don't want to get from a defense
attorney
so i called him up and he said you need
to be very careful because
there are some prosecutors who really
hate you and i said you know there needs
to be a firewall between above ground
and below ground activities and my job
is to
is to discuss is to bring these issues
into the open
so you know don't
don't really worry made him feel a lot
better anyway so
that said um i think one of the things
that makes very clear
a few things it makes very clear one of
them is that um
a decrease in economic activity is good
for the world
and um
and and also that the and i've known
this for a long time but this just made
this so clear
the the global economic the global the
global trade is incredibly vulnerable to
all sorts of disruptions
and um
a great example having to do with the
coronavirus is that
i started following the whole thing back
when it was still called
the wuhan virus i think um anyway they
shut down wuhan
and two days later
this this is the moment i started
following it is
so i'd heard yeah yeah yeah they're
shutting down wuhan that's
interesting but i don't know much about
it and then two days later
they closed a hyundai factory
in korea in south korea
and i thought wow
so a shutting down a city
you know thousands of miles away
caused this factory to shut down within
two days
and
the i understood before then that the
global economic system is incredibly
interdependent which is one of the
things by the way that really pisses me
off
is that all sorts of economists
understand that the global economic
system is interdependent
but if you try to talk about the same
interdependence in a forest
then they all of a sudden get really
stupid and they can see
that a an earthquake in japan
is going to raise timber prices in the
pacific northwest because it's going to
mean an
increase in demand for
trees to build new houses in japan they
understand that
but they don't understand that if you
wipe out a certain species of frog it's
going to have cascading
effects and anyway
um
so
i've read tons of history and i love
reading history
and i was reading military history when
i was
literally in third and fourth grade and
it's become clear to me that wars are
primarily won
not by
as as exciting and horrific as battles
are
that's not really where wars are won
that the american civil war
was kind of one at gettysburg and
vicksburg
but it was really one with a blockade
and was really one in the industrial
centers
of of the north as opposed to the south
and world war ii yeah a lot of it was
the eastern front
an awful lot of it was eastern front
but um the way you win a war is by
destroying the enemy's capacity to wage
war
and i think about this a lot i
i don't know about specific levers
i just know that the global economic
system is incredibly interdependent
um it is it has long supply lines which
are vulnerable um there has been a war
declared against the natural world for
at least the last 6 000 years
and
if space aliens were doing to the planet
what the dominant culture is doing
we would know exactly what to do and we
would go after
the infrastructure we would go after we
would destroy their capacity to wage war
but we get all confused
because this way we get computers and we
get
access to ice cream 24 7. and
you know louis mumford talked about that
as the magnificent bribe that why is it
that we've all surrendered so easily to
the modern authoritarians and
um it's basically because
they have collectively done a really
smart thing which is to make it so
a significant portion of the people have
a share of the goods and either that or
a promise of the share of the goods
and so the american dream will
keep people
uh basically
so long as you continue to give me
great health care
ice cream and somehow those two seem
mixed that if i eat enough ice cream i'm
gonna need the health care
uh and uh
car computer and uh
potato chips and an electric blanket
it's like i'm good i don't need penguins
i don't need insects i don't need a
living ocean
but that's part of it anyway so so what
we have to do
is to
it's like
i think about this all the time if
salmon could take on human manifestation
what would they do
and if so what i really want and i left
this off i forgot about this earlier
when i was
summing my work i think one of the
things that we need to do that's really
important is to
transfer our loyalty away from the
economic system
and toward uh
and toward the natural world and then
once you make your loyalty with the
natural world
your
your actions become more clear and then
and then things become technical
then it becomes you know how do you
defeat the system and
then at that point we can really
as as lea keith who's here as she says
we need to start thinking like
military strategists you know we need to
start looking at this as a war on the
world
and look at this how do we win how do we
stop them
and i think it's a really interesting i
think it's important and i think it's
also just a really interesting
thing again if we made a movie and they
were space aliens who were doing all
this
it would be a really exciting and fun
movie how we figure out how to
to stop them um
but as it is
uh we we have mixed loyalties
cool um arielle uh you had a question
above
uh yeah yeah um
long time fan derek thank you for this
uh i know you've gotten some criticism
for
uh your views on queer theory and third
wave feminism
so i'd be curious if you'd like to speak
a bit to how
how your views on those topics relate to
your larger philosophy
well thank you for that question too and
um
i think
queer theory is just an extraordinary
well do a couple things one is queer
theory is just an extraordinary thing
because it's there are some
remarkable thought errors that are
inherent in it
that i'm horrified that uh
all these people in academia who i mean
that's their job is to sit around and
think
and they don't seem to be doing such a
great job
um and queer theory is based on the idea
um it is uh
and this is their words not mine it is
a total strike against
anything that is normal so it is
this is this is their words that it
anything is normal
is oppressive that normality itself is
oppressive
and some of the arguments will and i've
seen these arguments made
many times the arguments can boil down
to
and they're especially interested in sex
and the arguments can boil down to
[Music]
so strictures against homosexuality
are clearly oppressive and wrong
therefore all strictures against all
forms of sexuality
are oppressive and wrong and
that just doesn't even pass like
fifth grade logic it's just and i
i am not this is not this is not me
being inflammatory this is
them making these arguments that
therefore
because strictly against homosexuality
are wrong
therefore strictures against pedophilia
are wrong therefore strictures against
bestiality are wrong
therefore strictures against necrophilia
are wrong those are those
i'm not making those up and it's
it's just crazy and we can't really talk
about that without talking about
something else that's been really
problematical oh my god
i hate that word problematically phase
that's another word that's been
destroyed
um something else i don't like let's
just say that post-modernism
and it does the same thing so i agree
the strictest against homosexuality are
wrong
i just don't agree with the next part
that therefore
and i'm going to back up even further in
post-modernism so there's
i wrote a book a few years ago
that uh it was about a struggle for the
soul of anarchism
and this book cost me my publisher two
publishers actually
cost me seven stories in p.m um
and in this book i
uh i argued that there are anarchists
who believe
that
governments exist primarily to serve
those in power and this is a pretty easy
case to make and a lot of anarchists
make this case
that governments i totally agree with
this
that if you just ask do governments take
better care of individuals or
corporations
you know i've asked 10 000 people that
and nobody has ever said they take
better care of individuals they take
better care of corporations
so corporations even exist i mean for
god's sake corporations are considered
people
so so on one hand you have anarchists
who believe that
that all the governments exist primarily
to set up rules that benefit others of
their class
makes perfect sense to me and
on the other hand you have anarchists
who believe that because
governments are set up primarily to
serve
governors and others of their class
therefore
all social rules are inherently
oppressive
and that's nuts and that's how you can
get like the magazine
anarchy of journal desire armed
dedicating an entire issue to promoting
pedophilia
because nobody can say because all
social restrictions
are inherently oppressive and again i
just think that's nuts and unfortunately
there are a lot of anarchists going all
the way back to diogenes
2500 years ago who who believe that
so now let's move forward to
post-modernism the post-modernism was in
some ways and this is just a really
short
version of it postmodernism was based on
the idea that there are various
uh narratives that inform
how we perceive the world absolutely
brilliant
and some narratives get more attention
paid to them
than other narratives and some
narratives are pushed by those in power
and absolutely brilliant completely
agree with that
that's why we hear how great columbus
was
but we don't hear that he was a slaver
you know we don't hear all the horrible
stuff
we didn't hear about it you know
pre-1960 very much
excuse me so postmodernism starts with
the idea
we need to unpack some of those various
narratives and see why some narratives
are given more credence than others
great idea
the problem is that their place they
ended up
is so ridiculous that it makes me
question whether humans are in fact
sentient
and the place they ended up is
well yeah there are a lot of competing
narratives therefore
there is nothing but narrative and
there's no reality
like what how did you get there
and that's just as silly as the whole
career theory thing with
just because
strictures against homosexuality are
wrong all strictures against all forms
of sexuality are wrong
both of those forget that we have to
come back to physical reality
and the physical reality is primary and
that
there is there are differences between
adults and children
there are differences in cognitive
ability there are differences in
ability to make rational decisions
when i was a kid
and i don't know how any children
survive
when i was a kid i'd seen i'd seen
people
jump off buildings in movies
and i never noticed they did a jump cut
in between so the person jumps off the
building
and then somebody lands on the ground
but you don't see the part in the middle
and so i jumped off the roof
and had a rude awakening when i landed
on the ground
unfortunately it was only a one story
building and so i just hit the ground
hard and
gotten owie as opposed to breaking
anything
but children do oh
children who am i kidding in my teens
after i got a driver's license it was
really considered fun
to drive down a country road and turn
off your headlights
and then drive through the night without
headlights what sort of idiotic person
would do that well
a 16 year old named derek would do that
and the point is children
children's brains are not developed and
so
two adults uh of the same sex
having sex is not the same anyway the
point is
that we always have to come back to
physical reality physical reality
is real and then um
and then you you build up from there one
of the problems with the postmodernists
is you know we really have a lot of
cancer culture today
and part of the reason for that is that
if you if your primary argument
well if you are arguing that
reality doesn't exist and there are all
these different stories the only way you
can win your argument is by is by
shutting the other people up
you can't use facts you can no longer
use facts if you don't believe that
there are actual facts
that's a very interesting thing too
really annoys me because i
have made those who've read my books no
i've made some critiques of science
there are valid critiques to make of
science
but the valid critiques don't include
that it's not real at all
it's just one way of knowing in the
world the main critique i have of
science is that it's not the only way
and there are things that are not
reproducible
such as uh willfulness
but that doesn't mean that that doesn't
mean that if i drop this leaf
it's not going to fall to the ground i
mean we still have the physical reality
of
i mean gravity still exists
and i always come back to that did that
answer your question at all ariel
yeah totally thank you
all right so we have about uh seven
minutes left uh we'll sneak
one more question in um and jen you had
a
question
hey derek um i'm gonna use a piece of
jargon in my question so feel free to
punt back and i can try my best to
define it
though i feel i'll stumble um my
question is uh what is your conception
of what malloc is um
what to you or the generator functions
or the causal drivers behind it um is
the essence of environmentalism a fight
against malloc
more than anything else um
i've heard the word malloc but i fear
that it's primarily been
in vincent price movies when i was a kid
so can you define malik please is that
the word you were
thinking about yeah yeah m-o-l-o-c-h oh
god i'm gonna stumble in this
um
a shitty a shitty tl dr would be malik
is kind of
that beast you can almost think of it as
its own organism
that has arisen to kind of swallow the
world it's kind of
the game theoretical equilibria that is
the system we put up
multiplied by human nature multiplied by
beliefs or the stories that we're at
that are behind securitization
financialization
corporatization technologization
it's this consuming of the world all the
flows of the world
into flows of value accretion that money
i think somebody said it really well
draining life energy for potential
energy which is what money is
um i don't know if that helps
well whether or not it helps is [ __ ]
brilliant
uh i love it and i also just want to say
i mean this is not angling for another
invitation but i want to say that your
questions are also great that i'd be
glad to do this again sometime
anyway um
i mean it's a huge question and another
way for me to try to define what my work
has been about my whole
life has been trying to find sort of
you know a unified field theory for this
culture's destructiveness
and a lot of it is patriarchy and
patriarchy's violation imperative
uh that springs from and
that inner sense of emptiness and you
try to fill it and you try to
fill your own brokenness by
violating others and by
pretending others are inferior to you
and
validating that in their inferiority by
violating them and that's insatiable
and then we can also talk about you know
lewis mumford's authoritarian techniques
where the
technologies actually get in charge and
that's a whole nother subject but
it's i mean our cities designed for
human beings are for automobiles
and is the economy designed for human
beings or for corporations or for the
technologies
and that the whole thing is run i mean
it's so funny that they talk about the
difficulty of getting off a fossil fuel
economy
or getting off an industrial economy
even though it's killing the planet even
though they acknowledge the harm it's
doing
it's like wow who is really in charge
and
and then i have to bring in uh jack
forbes book columbus and other cannibals
where he talks about
what he calls i don't know how to
pronounce it w-e-t-i-k-o
wedigo i guess we'll call it wedigo
disease
uh which he thinks he thought he's dead
now
it's a spiritual illness with a physical
vector
and this spiritual illness causes people
to
become vampires to consume the souls of
others
and it's a highly contagious disease and
you know we can talk about that we can
talk about the fact that
agricultural societies inherently
they convert the land base to humans
put it to human use and that does two
things one it causes them to
harm the land base therefore their way
of life has to be
based on expansion at the same time it
allows them to
have more humans which means they get to
have a soldier class
which also means that they get to
convert the land base into chariots of
war
and therefore they have a competitive
advantage over their neighbors
so we can talk about you know one bad
apple spoiling the bunch that way
so we can talk about this in terms of
sort of purely mechanistic material
forces
we can talk about it in terms of of
sociological forces like lewis mumford
does we can talk about it in terms of a
spiritual illness like jack forbes does
one of the reasons i wrote my book
dreams is because i wanted to just spend
one book exploring
the idea that there's like this cosmic
war going on
of uh i'm not sure i believe this but
you know like forces who wish the world
ill
and forces who wish the world well and
they're having a conflict like i said
different books are just exploring
different facets of this
and i threw the ideas out in dreams
maybe they're true i want to see i want
to explore them to the end and see if
they work
and i mean what is moloch
uh i mean it's not
one thing i can tell you it's not is
some people have written to me just very
smugly and said
you know derek you can ignore all your
analysis because the problem is just
greed
it's like well
greed's a part of it but what about a
social system that rewards greed
where does sociopathy fit in it's like i
did a talk years ago
15 20 years ago now um at bioneers
and it broke my heart because bioneers
is supposed to be about social change
but i was the only person there who was
talking about either
power or psychopathology and i don't
know how you can talk about
social change without talking about
power and i don't know how you can talk
about the murder of the plan without
talking about psychopathology
so where does psychopathology fit into
all this um
and you'll note by the way and here i am
doing the thing we talked about at the
beginning that i'm going to go ahead and
attack myself instead of you attacking
me
but you'll know i'm not actually
answering your question um
i'm just throwing out all sorts of ideas
because
26 books later i don't have an answer
and
i don't know that there is
an answer i think that there are
a whole bunch of answers some of which
i've tried to list out
so before we go how much time do we have
peter
we are at the hour but i'm cool to stay
a little bit longer if you are
um so i want for wait who asked that
last question
legend so i want for you to answer what
you think moloch is
i think what most resonates for me is
kind of i think what you hinted at
this idea that we still convince
ourselves that we're in control
and that things are for our goals but
not realizing
that we've birthed something and you can
think of technology also as
us birthing um a new form of life
and moloch corporations is a super
organism
and it's actually the one that's in
charge it's actually the one that's
devouring
the world um what exactly is it
um that's where this whole like game a
game b
thing is which is it's a set of norms
and
game theoretical structures it's an
equilibrium that maybe we could shift
but um i'm trying to understand also the
aspect that you're talking about which
is what is the human nature and
sociopathy and so on
well so thank you for all that i think
that's really great what you just said
and sociopaths have been in every
society
and the question really is what you do
with them in in some cultures
they would take them hunting and push
them off ice floes and in other cultures
they make them ceos and and
leaders and
you know i guess here's what i want to
close with which is ruth benedict
talked about why some cultures are to
use her word good and some are not so
good
and um
what she found is that the good cultures
recognize that humans are both selfish
and social and so they would destroy the
bifurcation
between selfishness and socialness
by praising acts that benefited the
group as a whole
and disallowing acts that benefited the
individual at the expense of the group
so if you do something that's really
selfish so i go out and get a bunch of
salmon
and i try to sell them to people then
you shame me for doing so
if on the other hand i go get a bunch of
salmon and then i distribute them to
everybody
then everybody says wow that's really
great you did that and you reward
that that socially beneficial behavior
and i can give everything away because i
know tomorrow somebody else is going to
go
gather huckleberries and they're going
to distribute those so what we're
building is social capital
and this is how healthy functioning
families work you know what at the
dinner table
nobody says junior will you pass the
potatoes and he says yeah that'll cost
you three dollars
i mean you do it because because you're
in relationships
cool the thing i love about this
conversation is
it manifests what we're talking about
before about
i think you know i don't know if
anybody's mind was changed on anything
today
but it uh i think it gave gave us
all a lot including me to uh
to ruminate on to chew over
that's what the hanging out at the store
is all about
so thank you derek for coming to the
store we'd love to have you back
and have a similar session like this
maybe a more interactive dialogue
session so a couple uh i'll do some
announcements
um right after this uh after i press
record ariel is gonna lead like a post
sense making conversation session um she
does something at the stoic called the
dangerous space on sundays where we can
discuss dangerous ideas in a kind of a
safe container
so we're going to discuss some of the
stuff that came up here uh today at 6 30
pm eastern time
brett weinstein is coming in to talk
about unity
uh ravenconnelly's going to be uh
hosting that that should be really fun
uh john zurzan is coming tomorrow uh to
do a talk on late stage civilization
that's at 6 30 p.m eastern time and we
got
so many freaking events coming up but
chomsky's coming in november
you can check out um the website right
there uh if you'd like to support us
on patreon we've been um doing free
events 400 free events since clovis
started
if you like uh to help us steal the
culture and on while we sit on this
digital porch
feel free to support us there that being
said derek thanks again
everyone thanks for coming out today
thanks so much thanks for great
questions